

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science · University of Exeter, United Kindom

Department of Computer Science, Innovation Center A1, University of Exeter - Streatham Campus, Exeter, EX4 4RN □ (+44) 07410-636616 | Isy@ieee.org / sl940@exeter.ac.uk | Songyuanli.github.io | Songyuanli.github.io

Short Bio

Mr. Songyuan Li is currently working toward the Ph.D. degree in Computer Science with the College of Engineering, Mathematics and Physical Sciences at the University of Exeter, United Kingdom, supervised by Dr. Jia Hu and Prof. Geyong Min.

Before that, he received the B.Eng. and M.Eng. degrees in Computer Science and Technology from the Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications, China, in 2018 and 2021, respectively. During his Master's career, he worked with Prof. Jiwei Huang and Prof. Bo Cheng, at the State Key Laboratory of Networking and Switching Technology, Beijing, China.

Thus far, he has published articles in several international journals and conference proceedings, including IEEE TCCN, IEEE TNSM, IJWGS, PPNA, IEEE ICWS, IEEE SCC, IEEE ISPA, etc. He also serves/served as the TPC member of IEEE SmartCNS, IEEE SEAI, and ICCEAI, and the reviewer for several international journals and conferences, including IEEE Access, International Journal of Communication Systems, IEEE/ACM CCGrid, IEEE VTC, EAI CollaborateCom, IEEE IUCC, etc.

Research Interests __

- Distributed Systems and Networks
- Distributed Machine Learning

- Services/Cloud/Edge Computing
- QoS Modeling and Optimization

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science

College of Engineering, Mathematics and Physical Sciences, University of Exeter

• Supervisors: Dr. Jia Hu, and Prof. Geyong Min.

M.Eng. in Computer Science and Technology

State Key Laboratory of Networking and Switching Technology,

Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications

- Supervisors: Prof. Jiwei Huang, and Prof. Bo Cheng.
- Thesis: "QoS-Aware Service Resource Scheduling and Optimization".

B.Eng. in Computer Science and Technology

School of Computer Science, Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications

- Cumulative Overall GPA: 85/100: Major GPA: 88/100.
- Thesis: "QoS Evaluation and Optimization for IoT Services in Edge Computing Architecture".

September 2014 - June 2018

September 2021 - Present

September 2018 - June 2021

Exeter, U.K.

Beijing, China

Beijing, China

Research Experience _____

High Performance Computing and Networking (HPCN) Research Group

September 2021 - Present

Research Assistant, University of Exeter

- · Joint cooperation and competition design of service caching and computation offloading in mobile edge computing.
- QoS-aware service/resource provisioning for IoT-edge-cloud inference.
- Multi-agent coordination design based on distributed reinforcement learning.

State Key Laboratory of Networking and Switching Technology

Research Assistant, Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications

March 2016 - August 2021

Beijing, China

- QoS-aware service selection/composition based on service ecosystem.
- Market-oriented resource pricing, and demand allocation in cloud environments.
- QoS/QoE-aware decentralized resource management and task scheduling in IoT-edge-cloud systems.

SONGYUAN LI · CURRICULUM VITAE FEBRUARY 20, 2022

Exeter, U.K.

Research Projects

Performance Evaluation and Optimization of IoT Service System based on Edge Computing Architecture

National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 61972414)

January 2020 - Present

- Adopt the potential game theory to solve the edge resource allocation problem with QoE maximization in a decentralized manner.
- Study the dynamic QoS-aware task scheduling and resource management problem in mobile edge computing, through designing an efficient optimization algorithm with LP relaxation techniques.

Self-Adaptive Scheme of Software Ecosystem with Collaborative Learning among Humans, Machines and Services

National Key Research and Development Program of China (No. 2018YFB1003804)

October 2018 - Present

- Propose a price-incentive resource auction mechanism, with the objective of stimulating maximum users willing to purchase cloud resources.
- Design a market-oriented cloud pricing strategy which solves the resource pricing and demand allocation for revenue maximization.
- Develop a QoS-aware concurrent service selection approach, with the max-min fairness across multiple service requests achieved.

QoS Evaluation Research for Large-Scale Dynamic Service Environment

March 2016 - December 2018

National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 61502043)

- Design queueing network models for QoS evaluation of IoT services in edge-cloud systems.
- Conduct reliability-aware QoS evaluation for recoverable IoT edge services using the modeling techniques of generalized stochastic Petri nets.

Service Composition in IoT Environment

March 2016 - December 2018

Beijing Natural Science Foundation (No. 4162042)

• Manipulate the Markov-Decision-Process-based resource allocation and task scheduling in edge computing paradigm weighing energy costs against QoS requirements.

Honours & Awards

Outstanding Master Dissertation Award (top 1%)

Beijing Municipal Education Commission, China

2021

Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications, China

2021

Outstanding Postgraduate Student Award (top 5%)

2018, 2019, 2020

First-Class Postgraduate Scholarship

Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications, China

China National Scholarship (top 2%)

Ministry of Education of the P.R. China

Outstanding Postgraduate Student Award

State Key Laboratory of Network and Switching Technology, Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications, China

2019 ina

2019

Outstanding Bachelor Dissertation Award (top 3%)

Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications, China

• First Prize in China Undergraduate Mathematical Contest in Modeling (Beijing Region)

2016

Publications

Journal Publications

- J5. **[TCCN'21] S. Li**, J. Huang, J. Hu, and B. Cheng, **QoE-DEER: A QoE-Aware Decentralized Resource Allocation Scheme for Edge Computing**, IEEE Transactions on Cognitive Communications and Networking, *Early Access, accepted on September 29*, 2021.
- J4. [TNSM'21] S. Li, J. Huang, and B. Cheng, Resource Pricing and Demand Allocation for Revenue Maximization in laaS Clouds: A Market-Oriented Approach, IEEE Transactions on Network and Service Management, vol. 18, no. 3, pp. 3460-3475, 2021.
- J3. **[TNSM'21] S. Li**, J. Huang, and B. Cheng, **A Price-Incentive Resource Auction Mechanism Balancing the Interests Between Users and Cloud Service Provider**, IEEE Transactions on Network and Service Management, *vol. 18, no. 2, pp. 2030-2045, 2021*.
- J2. [PPNA'20] J. Huang, S. Li, and Y. Chen, Revenue-Optimal Task Scheduling and Resource Management for IoT Batch Jobs in Mobile Edge Computing, Peer-to-Peer Networking and Applications, vol. 13, no. 5, pp. 1776-1787, 2020.
- J1. **[IJWGS'18]** J. Huang, **S. Li**, Y. Chen, and J. Chen, **Performance Modelling and Analysis for IoT Services**, International Journal of Web and Grid Services, vol. 14, no. 2, pp. 146-169, 2018.

Conference Publications

- C3. **[ICWS'19] S. Li**, J. Huang, B. Cheng, L. Cui and Y. Shi, **FASS: A Fairness-Aware Approach for Concurrent Service Selection with Constraints**, Proc. of IEEE International Conference on Web Services, *July 8-13, 2019, Milan, Italy.*
- C2. [ISPA'17] S. Li, and J. Huang, Energy Efficient Resource Management and Task Scheduling for IoT Services in Edge Computing Paradigm, Proc. of IEEE International Symposium on Parallel and Distributed Processing with Applications, *December 12-15, 2017, Guangzhou, China.*
- C1. **[SCC'17] S. Li**, and J. Huang, **GSPN-Based Reliability-Aware Performance Evaluation of IoT Services**, Proc. of IEEE International Conference on Service Computing, *June 25-30, 2017, Honolulu, Hawaii, USA.*

Selected Talks

Models and Solutions of QoS Optimization for Services Ecosystem

July 2021

Services Computing Seminar, China University of Petroleum - Beijing, China

Professional Services

Technical Program Committee

- IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering and Artificial Intelligence, SEAI 2022
- IEEE International Conference on Smart Computing, Networking and Services, SmartCNS 2021
- International Conference on Computer Engineering and Artificial Intelligence, ICCEAI 2021

Journal Reviewer

- International Journal of Communication Systems (Wiley), 2022
- IEEE Access, 2021, 2020
- Scientific Programming (Hindawi), 2021, 2020
- Behaviour & Information Technology (Taylor & Francis), 2020

Conference Reviewer

- IEEE/ACM 22nd International Symposium on Cluster, Cloud and Internet Computing, CCGrid 2022
- IEEE 20th International Conference on Ubiquitous Computing and Communications, IUCC 2021
- IEEE 4th International Conference on Data Science and Computational Intelligence, DSCI 2021
- IEEE International Conference on Electrical, Computer, and Energy Technologies, ICECET 2021
- IEEE International Conference on Electrical, Computer, Communications, and Mechatronics Engineering, ICECCME 2021
- EAI 16th International Conference on Collaborative Computing, CollaborateCom 2020
- IEEE 92nd Vehicular Technology Conference, VTC2020-Fall